<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thalaba the Destroyer (1801)</title>
            <author>Robert Southey</author>

            <editor xml:id="ebb">Elisa E. Beshero-Bondar</editor>


            <sponsor>
               <orgName>Center for the Digital Text</orgName>
            </sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor>
            <principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal>

            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI P5 encoding by</resp>
               <persName>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName>

            </respStmt>

         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>digital edition in TEI, date: 18 Sept. 2014. P5.</edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Center for the Digital Text at the University of Pittsburgh at
               Greensburg</authority>
            <pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace>
            <date>2013</date>
            <availability>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                  License</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This text is based on the Project Gutenberg eBook of <bibl>
                  <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> by <author>Robert Southey</author>
                  <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                  <publisher>PRINTED FOR T. N. LONGMAN AND O. REES</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>PATERNOSTER-ROW, London</pubPlace>
                  <publisher>BY BIGGS AND COTTLE</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Bristol</pubPlace>,<date>1801</date>. </bibl> Release date: <date/>
               [Ebook #39804] Public domain in the USA. <ref
                  target="http://www.gutenberg.org/files/39804/39804-h/39804-h.htm"/></p>
            <p>This eBook is for the use of anyone anywhere at no cost and with almost no
               restrictions whatsoever. You may copy it, give it away or re-use it under the terms
               of the Project Gutenberg License included with this eBook or online at
               www.gutenberg.org/license</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Encoded with careful attention to the semantic association of text and paratext
               structures. Southey's paratext notes are encoded as hierarchical descendants of the
               line-group or other portion of Southey's main text on the spot where they are
               signalled. This is not only conformant with TEI standard practice but also is
               designed to help investigate semantic interlinkage of text and paratext in this
               heavily annotated epic poem. Encoding of proper names, especially places, people, and
               collectives is designed to trace associations made between text and paratext.
               References to places in the main text are encoded to determine whether they are
               mentioned literally, as places visited by the characters in the poem, or imagined
               referentially by analogy.</p>
            <p>This edition does not, however, attempt to reproduce the title page or page layout of
               the 1801 edition. Instead, the TEI is prepared to be the basis of a digital edition
               optimized for viewing text and paratext in association on a computer screen. This
               encoding responds to the print edition's layout of footnotes positioned beneath the
               main text, and is intended to assist experimental screen layouts that preserve this
               association of text and paratext.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2017-05-07" resp="#ebb">Revised this header to include a proper revisionDesc
            changelog. Edited file to represent Center for the Digital Text as sponsoring
            organization. Added a front element to move prefatory material inside in the single-file
            edition to improve TEI conformance. Also prepared the original single-file edition to be
            transformed into a collection of smaller files for ease of processing. Added @xml:ids to
            number the volume divs.</change>
         <change when="2016" resp="#ebb">Added attributes to distinguish between analogous places
            and literal physical movement of characters, and wrote Schemtaron rules to control
            this.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <head>
            <bibl>
               <title level="m">Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (<date>1801</date>) by <author>Robert
                  Southey</author>
            </bibl>
         </head>
         <epigraph>

            <q>
               <lg xml:lang="grc">
                  <l> Ποιηματων αϰρατης η ελευϑερια, ϰαι νομος εις,</l>
                  <l>το δοξαν τω ϖοιητη.</l>
               </lg>
               <bibl>
                  <author>Lucian</author>, <title>Quomodo Hist. scribenda.</title>
               </bibl>
            </q>
         </epigraph>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="toc">
            <list>
               <item>THE FIRST VOLUME.<list>
                     <item><ref target="vol_1/Book_1.xml">THE FIRST BOOK.</ref></item>
                     <item><ref target="vol_1/Book_2.xml">THE SECOND BOOK.</ref></item>
                     <item><ref target="vol_1/Book_3.xml">THE THIRD BOOK.</ref></item>
                     <item><ref target="vol_1/Book_4.xml">THE FOURTH BOOK.</ref></item>
                     <item><ref target="vol_1/Book_5.xml">THE FIFTH BOOK.</ref></item>
                  </list></item>
               <item>THE SECOND VOLUME.<list>
                     <item><ref target="vol_2/Book_6.xml">THE SIXTH BOOK.</ref></item>
                     <item><ref target="vol_2/Book_7.xml">THE SEVENTH BOOK.</ref></item>
                     <item><ref target="vol_2/Book_8.xml">THE EIGHTH BOOK.</ref></item>
                     <item><ref target="vol_2/Book_9.xml">THE NINTH BOOK.</ref></item>
                     <item><ref target="vol_2/Book_10.xml">THE TENTH BOOK.</ref></item>
                     <item><ref target="vol_2/Book_11.xml">THE ELEVENTH BOOK.</ref></item>
                     <item><ref target="vol_2/Book_12.xml">THE TWELFTH BOOK.</ref></item>
                  </list></item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <head>PREFACE</head>


            <p>In the continuation of the <bibl>Arabian Tales</bibl>, the
                  <orgName>Domdaniel</orgName> is mentioned; a Seminary for evil Magicians <rs
                  type="metaplace" subtype="under" ref="Under_Ocean">under the Roots of the
               Sea</rs>. From this seed the present Romance has grown. Let me not be supposed to
               prefer the metre in which it is written, abstractedly considered, to the regular
               blank verse; the noblest measure, in my judgement, of which our admirable language is
               capable. For the following Poem I have preferred it, because it suits the varied
               subject; it is the <hi rend="italic">Arabesque</hi> ornament of an Arabian tale.</p>

            <p>The <bibl>dramatic sketches of <author>
                     <persName>Dr. Sayer</persName>
                  </author>
               </bibl>, a volume which no lover of poetry will recollect without pleasure, induced
               me when a young versifier, to practise in this metre. I felt that while it gave the
               poet a wider range of expression, it satisfied the ear of the reader. It were easy to
               make a parade of learning by enumerating the various feet which it admits; it is only
               needful to observe that no two lines are employed in <hi rend="italic">sequence</hi>
               which can be read into one. Two six-syllable lines (it will perhaps be answered)
               compose an Alexandrine: the truth is that the Alexandrine, when harmonious, is
               composed of two six-syllable lines.</p>

            <p>One advantage this metre assuredly possesses; the dullest reader cannot distort it
               into discord: he may read it with a <hi rend="italic">prose mouth</hi>, but its flow
               and fall will still be perceptible. Verse is not enough favoured by the English
               reader: perhaps this is owing to the obtrusiveness, the regular Jews-harp <hi
                  rend="italic">twing-twang</hi>, of what has been foolishly called heroic measure.
               I do not wish the <hi rend="italic">improvisatorè</hi> tune, but something that
               denotes the sense of harmony, something like the accent of feeling; like the tone
               which every Poet necessarily gives to Poetry.</p>

         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
