<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="SchematronThalaba.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thalaba the Destroyer (1801)</title>
            <author>Robert Southey</author>

            <editor>Elisa E. Beshero-Bondar</editor>


            <sponsor>
               <orgName>Integrated Digital Humanities</orgName>
            </sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor>
            <principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal>

            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI P5 encoding by</resp>
               <persName>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName>
            </respStmt>

         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>digital edition in TEI, date: 27 June 2013. P5.</edition>

         </editionStmt>

         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Integrated Digital Humanities at the University of Pittsburgh at
               Greensburg</authority>
            <pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace>
            <date instant="false">2013</date>
            <availability default="false" status="unknown">
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                  License</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>

         <notesStmt>
            <note anchored="true">Any special notes on this text? (optional)</note>
            <note anchored="true">You can have multiple notes here.</note>
         </notesStmt>

         <sourceDesc default="false">
            <p part="N">This text is based on the Project Gutenberg eBook of <bibl default="false"
                  status="draft">
                  <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> by <author>Robert Southey</author>
                  <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                  <publisher>PRINTED FOR T. N. LONGMAN AND O. REES</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>PATERNOSTER-ROW, London</pubPlace>
                  <publisher>BY BIGGS AND COTTLE</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Bristol</pubPlace>,<date instant="false">1801</date>. </bibl> Release
               date: <date instant="false"/> [Ebook #39804] Public domain in the USA. </p>
            <p part="N">This eBook is for the use of anyone anywhere at no cost and with almost no
               restrictions whatsoever. You may copy it, give it away or re-use it under the terms
               of the Project Gutenberg License included with this eBook or online at
               www.gutenberg.org/license</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl default="false">
            <p part="N">Describes our editorial practice.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>
               <bibl default="false" status="draft">
                  <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (<date instant="false">1801</date>) by
                  <author>Robert Southey</author>
               </bibl>
            </head>
            <div type="volume">
               <head>THE SECOND VOLUME.</head>
               <div type="book" xml:id="Book_9">
                  
                  <head>THE NINTH BOOK.</head>
                
               <lg xml:id="B9_lg553">
                  <l rend="i0" n="4922">Then Maimuna grew pale, as <placeName ref="Mohareb_City">thro the bars</placeName></l>
                  <l rend="i0" n="4923">She saw the Martyr pendant by the feet,</l>
                  <l rend="i0" n="4924">His gold locks hanging downwards, and she cried,</l>
                  <l rend="i4" n="4925">"This is <rs type="person" ref="Khawla">my Sister</rs>'s deed!</l>
                  <l rend="i4" n="4926">"O Thalaba, for us,</l>
                  <l rend="i0" n="4927"><rs type="religion" subtype="Christian">"Not for his faith the red-haired Christian dies.</rs></l>
                  
                     <l rend="i0" n="4928">"She wants the foam<ref target="#N_160">
                        <note type="author" anchored="true" xml:id="N_160">
                           <p part="N"><rs type="science" subtype="chem"> A Physician of <placeName>Ragusa</placeName>
                            was deputed by <rs type="place" ref="Ragusa">that little Republic</rs>
                              to negotiate with the Emperor of the Turks. Before he embarked on
                              this voyage he took into his service a boy of a red complection,
                              the only son of a widow, a poor woman, but a woman of honour and
                                 virtuous. This Envoy on his arrival at <placeName>Constantinople</placeName> immediately
                              addressed himself to the first Physician of his imperial highness,
                              that thro' his favour he might have more access to negociate for
                              his country. he Mahometan had no sooner set eyes on the young
                              Ragusan, than he employed every artifice to induce his master to
                              leave him. The boy himself, at last, wishing to remain at
                              <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>, flattered by the fair prospects that were held out
                              to him, and touched with a tender and heroic compassion for her who
                              had given him birth, prayed his protector to leave him with the
                              Barbarian, and carry to his mother the money which on that account
                              he would receive: So that the Ragusan physician left his servant to
                             the Byzantian, and received from him a purse of a thousand sequins.
                              After some days the Italian went to take leave of the Mohammedan
                                 Physician, and to thank him for his favours; and he requested
                              earnestly to see the red-headed boy before his departure. The Turk
                              was obliged to own he had made poison of him, and led him into a
                              chamber where the naked body of the boy was still suspended by the
                              feet. The first master of the red-headed boy was greatly surprized
                              at the sight and still more so when he heard that the boy had been
                              beaten upon the belly for six hours, by slaves who relieved one
                              another, till he died: and that a poison was made of the last foam
                              that came from his mouth, so penetrating, that if the stirrup of a
                              horse were touched with the point of a pin that had been dipt in
                              it, he who should mount would immediately die.</rs> <bibl default="false" status="draft">Plaidoyers Historiques par M.
                                 Tristan.</bibl> 1650. </p>
                           <p part="N"> In this volume the pleadings of the Mother against the
                              Ragusan physician, and his defence are given. The Mother says, it
                              is impossible that he, being a Physician himself, should not have
                              known for what the Infidel Physician wanted to purchase a
                              red-headed boy, as he himself would have made the same use of him
                              had he not been afraid of the laws, the rest is in the usual stile
                              of <bibl>Tristan's rhetoric</bibl>. </p>
                           <p part="N"> As 
                              <rs type="religion" subtype="Islam">the Moslem</rs>
                            employed a red-headed <rs type="religion" subtype="Christian">Christian</rs>
                            in this manufactory, it should seem that a Turk ought to be used in
                              <placeName>Christendom</placeName>. But as Turks are not easily caught, a <rs type="religion" subtype="Judaism">Jew</rs> might do. </p>
                           <p part="N"> In the <placeName>Islands of Barlovento</placeName> and in all the country of
                              <placeName>Brazil</placeName>, in <placeName>Santa Marta</placeName> and in <rs type="place">the new kingdom</rs>, and in other
                              countries, where a cruel sort of Indians inhabited, they used
                              another sort of poison; for they would take the leg of an Indian
                                 whom they had killed, and hang it up in the air against the sun,
                              and fill it with many barbs of poisoned arrows, which were taken
                              out of the flesh of an Indian, which after some days they took out,
                              and without cleansing of them, they dried them in the air where the
                              sun did not come, and then they headed their arrows with them; and
                              that became the most malevolent poison, and the most hard to be
                              cured in the world. After the Spaniards came into that country and
                              waged war upon the Indians, they then made it with the flesh of
                              Spaniards, whom they killed or took; but more particularly they
                              desired the flesh of some red-headed Spaniard, whose hairs were of
                              a deep saffron colour; for they were of opinion that there was more
                              heat in that flesh, and consequently more virulency in the poison
                              which it produced: but perhaps they may have heard it often said
                              amongst the Spaniards themselves, that red-headed men are fit to
                              make a composition of poison. <bibl default="false" status="draft">Garcilasso's Royal Commentaries of <placeName>Peru</placeName>.</bibl>
                           </p>
                           <p part="N">
                              <q>"Three ounces of a red-haired wench"</q> were among the
                              ingredients of the witch-caldron in <bibl default="false" status="draft">
                                 <title>Macbeth</title>
                              </bibl>. <rs type="science" subtype="diag">Why red-hair was supposed to be a symptom of leprosy, was
                                 one of the questions proposed by Michaelis to Niebuhr and his
                                 fellow-travellers for investigation.</rs> It is singular that at the
                              time when these opinions prevailed universally, golden locks should
                              enter into almost every description of female beauty. If the word
                              of a poet may he taken (and the rhymer now quoted cannot be
                              suspected of invention enough for a lie,) the ladies even wore red
                              wigs, for he says of Absalom 
                           </p>
                           <q>
                              <lg xml:lang="es">
                                 <l rend="i0" part="N">Hasta los hombros pende su cabello</l>
                                 <l rend="i0" part="N">Mas que el oro de <placeName>Arabia</placeName> roxo y bello.</l>
                              </lg>
                              <lg xml:lang="es">
                                 <l rend="i0" part="N">Cada año qual renuevo lo cortava</l>
                                 <l rend="i1" part="N">A damas se vendia para ornato.</l>
                                 <l rend="i8" part="N">
                                    <hi rend="italic"><bibl>
                                       David, del <author>Doctor Jacobo Uziel</author>.
                                    </bibl></hi>
                                 </l>
                              </lg>
                           </q>
                           <q>
                              <lg>
                                 <l rend="i0" part="N">Adown his shoulders his long tresses
                                    roll'd,</l>
                                 <l rend="i0" part="N">More beautiful and red than Eastern
                                    gold,</l>
                                 <l rend="i0" part="N">And annual as he cropt, the envied
                                    hair</l>
                                 <l rend="i0" part="N">Was yearly sold to ornament the fair.</l>
                              </lg>
                           </q>
                           <p part="N"> The Javanese had a method of procuring poison similar to
                              the Turkish receipt which I have employed. </p>
                           <p part="N"> The Cameleon, or Indian Salamander, otherwise called
                              Gekko. </p>
                           <p part="N"> This creature, which is not only found in <placeName ref="Brazil">Brasil</placeName>, but
                              also in the <placeName ref="Java">Isle of Java</placeName>, belonging to the <placeName>East Indies</placeName>, and which
                              by our people is called Gekko, from its constant cry, (like among
                              us that of the Cuckoe) is properly an Indian Salamander. It is
                              about a foot long, its skin of of a pale or sea green colour, with
                              red spots. The head is not unlike that of a tortoise, with a
                              streight mouth. The eyes are very large, starting out of the head,
                              with long and small eye-apples. The tail is distinguished by
                              several white rings; its teeth are so sharp as to make an
                              impression even upon steel. Each of its four legs had five crooked
                              claws aimed on the end with nails. Its gait is very slow, but
                              wherever it fastens it is not easily removed. It dwells commonly
                              upon rotten trees, or among the ruines of old houses and churches;
                              it oftentimes settles near the bedsteads, which makes sometimes the
                              moors pull down their huts. </p>
                           <p part="N"> Its constant cry is <hi rend="italic">gekko</hi>, but
                              before it begins it makes a kind of hissing noise. The sting of
                              this creature is so venomous, that the wound proves mortal, unless
                              it be immediately burnt with a red hot iron, or cut off. The blood
                              is of a palish colour, resembling poison itself. </p>
                           <p part="N"> The Javanese use to dip their arrows in the blood of this
                              creature; and those who deal in poisons among them, (an art much
                              esteemed in the <geogFeat>island</geogFeat> of <placeName>Java</placeName>, by both sexes) hang it up with a
                              string tied to the tail on the cieling, by which means it being
                              exasperated to the highest pitch sends forth a yellow liquor out of
                              its mouth, which they gather in small pots set underneath, and
                              afterwards coagulate into a body in the sun. This they continue for
                              several months together, by giving daily food to the creature. It
                              is unquestionably the strongest poison in <placeName>the world</placeName>; its urine
                              being of so corrosive a quality, that it not only raises blisters,
                              wherever it touches the skin, but turns the flesh black, and causes
                              a gangrene. <bibl default="false" status="draft">Nieuhoff.</bibl>
                           </p>
                           <p part="N"> Is there any analogy between a foam thus procured and the
                              saliva of a mad dog?</p>
                        </note>
                     </ref> that in his agony,</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="4938">"Last from his lips shall fall,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="4939">"The deadliest poison that <name type="divin">the Devils</name> know.</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="4940">"Son of Hodeirah, thou and I</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="4941">"Shall prove its deadly force!"</l>
                  
               </lg>
               
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
