<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="../../SchematronThalaba.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thalaba the Destroyer (1801), Volume 2: Book 10</title>
            <author>Robert Southey</author>
            <editor xml:id="ebb">Elisa E. Beshero-Bondar</editor>
            <sponsor>
               <orgName>Center for the Digital Text</orgName>
            </sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor>
            <principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI P5 encoding by</resp>
               <persName>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName>

            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>digital edition in TEI, date: 18 Sept. 2014. P5.</edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Center for the Digital Text at the University of Pittsburgh at
               Greensburg</authority>
            <pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace>
            <date>2013</date>
            <availability>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                  License</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This text is based on the Project Gutenberg eBook of <bibl>
                  <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> by <author>Robert Southey</author>
                  <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                  <publisher>PRINTED FOR T. N. LONGMAN AND O. REES</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>PATERNOSTER-ROW, London</pubPlace>
                  <publisher>BY BIGGS AND COTTLE</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Bristol</pubPlace>,<date>1801</date>. </bibl> Release
               date: <date/> [Ebook #39804] Public domain in the USA. <ref target="http://www.gutenberg.org/files/39804/39804-h/39804-h.htm"/>
            </p>
            <p>This eBook is for the use of anyone anywhere at no cost and with almost no
               restrictions whatsoever. You may copy it, give it away or re-use it under the terms
               of the Project Gutenberg License included with this eBook or online at
               www.gutenberg.org/license</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Encoded with careful attention to the semantic association of text and paratext structures. Southey's paratext notes are encoded as hierarchical descendants of the line-group or other portion of Southey's main text on the spot where they are signalled. This is not only conformant with TEI standard practice but also is designed to help investigate semantic interlinkage of text and paratext in this heavily annotated epic poem. Encoding of proper names, especially places, people, and collectives is designed to trace associations made between text and paratext. References to places in the main text are encoded to determine whether they are mentioned literally, as places visited by the characters in the poem, or imagined referentially by analogy.</p>
            <p>This edition does not, however, attempt to reproduce the title page or page layout of the 1801 edition. Instead, the TEI is prepared to be the basis of a digital edition optimized for viewing text and paratext in association on a computer screen. This encoding responds to the print edition's layout of footnotes positioned beneath the main text, and is intended to assist experimental screen layouts that preserve this association of text and paratext.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2017-05-07" resp="#ebb">Revised this header to include a proper revisionDesc changelog. Edited file to represent Center for the Digital Text as sponsoring organization. Added a front element to move prefatory material inside in the single-file edition to improve TEI conformance. Also prepared the original single-file edition to be transformed into a collection of smaller files for ease of processing. Added @xml:ids to number the volume divs.</change>
         <change when="2016" resp="#ebb">Added attributes to distinguish between analogous places and literal physical movement of characters, and wrote Schemtaron rules to control this.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <head>
            <bibl>
               <title level="m">Thalaba the Destroyer</title>
               <title level="a">, Volume 2: Book 10</title> (<date>1801</date>) by <author>Robert Southey</author>
            </bibl>
         </head>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="book" xml:id="Book_10">
                  <head>THE TENTH BOOK.</head>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg560">
                     <l rend="i0" n="4967">Alone, beside a rivulet it stands</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="4968">The Upas
                           <note type="author" anchored="true" xml:id="N_161">
                              <p> The fiction of the Upas is too well known from the Botanic Garden,
                                 to need repetition. Suffice it here to remark that the Tree is said
                                 to have sprung up as a punishment to the guilty Islanders. </p>
                              <p> None of our early travellers mention this Tree, and they were too
                                 fond of wonders to omit so monstrous a tale, had it been true. It
                                 is curious that such a story should have been invented by a
                                 Dutchman. </p>
                              <p> Perhaps the seed of the Upas is contained in the following
                                 passage. </p>
                              <p> Neere unto the said Iland (Java) is another countrey called
                                 Panten, or Tathalamasin. In this land there are trees yeelding
                                 meale, hony and wine, and the most deadly poison in all <placeName ref="the_world">the whole world</placeName>: for against it
                                 there is but one onley remedy; and that is this; if a man hath
                                 taken of the poyson, and would be delivered from the danger
                                 thereof, let him temper the dung of aman in water, and so drinke a
                                 good quantity thereof and it expels the poyson immediately.
                                    <bibl>Odoricus the Minorite Frier. In Hakluyt.</bibl>
                              </p>
                           </note>
                         Tree of Death.</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="4969">Thro' barren banks the barren waters flow,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="4970">The fish that meets them in the unmingling sea</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="4971">Floats poisoned on the waves.</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="4972">Tree grows not near, nor bush, nor flower, nor herb,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="4973">
                        <placeName ref="Earth_planet">The Earth</placeName> has
                        lost its parent powers of life</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="4974">And the fresh dew of Heaven that there descends,</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="4975">Steams in rank poison up.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg561">
                     <l rend="i0" n="4976">Before the appointed Youth and Maimuna</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="4977">Saw the first struggle of the dying throng,</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="4978">Crash sunk their prison wall!</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="4979">The whirlwind wrapt them round;</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="4980">Borne in the Chariot of the Winds</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="4981">Ere there was time to fear, their way was past,</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="4982">And lo! again they stand</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="4983">In the cave-dwelling of the blue-eyed Witch.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg562">
                     <l rend="i0" n="4984">Then came the weakness of her natural age</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="4985">At once on Maimuna;</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="4986">The burthen of her years</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="4987">Fell on her, and she knew</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="4988">That her repentance in the sight of<name type="divin">God</name>
                     </l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="4989">Had now found favour, and her hour was come.</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="4990">Her death was like the righteous; "Turn my face</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="4991">"To <placeName>Mecca</placeName>!" in her languid
                        eyes.</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="4992">The joy of certain hope</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="4993">Lit a last lustre, and in death</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="4994">The smile was on her cheek.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg563">
                     <l rend="i2" n="4995">No faithful
                           <note type="author" anchored="true" xml:id="N_162">
                              <p> When any person is to be buried, it is usual to bring the corpse
                                 at mid-day or afternoon prayers, to one or other of these Mosques,
                                 from whence it is accompanied by the greatest part of the
                                 congregation, <rs type="metaplace" subtype="under" ref="Tombs">to
                                    the grave</rs>. Their processions, at these times, are not so
                                 slow and solemn as in most parts of
                                    <placeName>Christendom</placeName>: for the whole company make
                                 what haste they can, singing as they go along, some select verses
                                 of their Coran. That absolute submission which they pay to the will
                                 of God, allows them not to use any consolatory words upon these
                                 occasions: no loss or misfortune is to be hereupon regretted or
                                 complained of: instead likewise of such expressions of sorrow and
                                 condolence, as may regard the deceased, the compliments turn upon
                                 the person, who is the nearest concerned, a blessing (say his
                                 friends) be upon your head. <bibl>Shaw.</bibl>
                              </p>
                              <p> All Mahometans inter the dead at the hour set apart for prayer;
                                 the defunct is not kept in the house, except he expires after
                                 sunset, but the Body is transported to the Mosque, whither it is
                                 carried by those who are going to prayer; each from a spirit of
                                 devotion is desirous to carry in his turn. Women regularly go on
                                 Friday to weep over, and pray <rs type="metaplace" subtype="under" ref="Tombs">at the sepulchres of the dead</rs>, whose memory
                                 they hold dear. <bibl>Chenier.</bibl>
                              </p>
                              <p> This custom of crowding about a funeral contributes to spread the
                                 plague in <placeName>Turkey</placeName>.—It is not many years
                                 since, in some parts of Worcestershire, the mourners were
                                 accustomed to kneel with their heads upon the coffin during the
                                 burial service. </p>
                              <p> The fullest account of a Mohammedan funeral is in the Lettres sur
                                 la Grece, of M. Guys. Chance made him the spectator of a ceremony
                                 which the Moslem will not suffer an Infidel to prophane by his
                                 presence. </p>
                              <p> "About ten in the morning I saw the grave-digger at work; the
                                 slaves and the women of the family were seated in the burial
                                 ground, many other women arrived, and then they all began to
                                 lament. After this prelude they one after the other embraced one of
                                 the little pillars which are placed upon the graves, crying out <hi rend="italic">Ogloum, ogloum, sœna Mussaphir gueldi</hi>, My
                                 Son, my Son, a guest is coming to see thee. At these words their
                                 tears and sobs began anew; but the storm did not continue long;
                                 they all seated themselves, and entered into conversation. </p>
                              <p> At noon I heard a confused noise, and cries of lamentation, it was
                                 the funeral which arrived. A Turk preceded it, bearing upon his
                                 head a small chest; four other Turks carried the bier upon their
                                 shoulders, then came the father, the relations and the friends of
                                 the dead in great numbers. Their cries ceased at the entrance of
                                 the burial ground, but then they quarrelled—and for this. The man
                                 who bore the chest opened it, it was filled with copies of the
                                 Koran, a croud of Turks, young and old, threw themselves upon the
                                 books and scrambled for them. Those who succeeded ranged themselves
                                 around the Iman, and all at once began to recite the Koran, almost
                                 as Boys say their lesson. Each of the readers received ten parats,
                                 about fifteen sols, wrapt in paper. It was then for these fifteen
                                 pence that these pious assistants had quarrelled, and in our own
                                 country you might have seen them fight for less. </p>
                              <p> The bier was placed by the grave, in which the grave-digger was
                                 still working, and perfumes were burnt by it. After the reading of
                                 the Koran the Iman chanted some Arabic prayers, and his full-chant
                                 would, no doubt, have appeared to you, as it did to me, very
                                 ridiculous. All the Turks were standing; they held their hands open
                                 over the grave, and answered <hi rend="italic">Amen</hi> to all the
                                 prayers which the Iman addressed to<name type="divin">God</name>for
                                 the deceased. </p>
                              <p> The prayers finished, a large chest was brought about six feet
                                 long and three broad; its boards were very thick. The coffin is
                                 usually made of cypress; thus literally is verified the phrase of <bibl>
                                    <author>Horace</author>
                                 </bibl> that the cypress is our last possession. </p>
                              <q>
                                 <lg xml:lang="la">
                                    <l rend="i0">Neque harum, quas colis, arborum,</l>
                                    <l rend="i0">Te, præter invisas cupressus,</l>
                                    <l rend="i0">Ulla brevem dominum sequetur.</l>
                                 </lg>
                              </q>
                              <p>
                                 <rs type="metaplace" subtype="under" ref="Tombs">The
                                    cemeteries</rs>
                                 <rs type="place" ref="Turkey">of the Turks</rs> are usually planted
                                 with these trees, to which they have a religious attachment. The
                                 chest which was in loose pieces, having been placed in the grave,
                                 the coffin was laid in it, and above planks, with other pieces of
                                 wood. Then all the Turks, taking spades, cast earth upon the grave
                                 to cover it. This is a part of the ceremony at which all the
                                 bystanders assisted in their turn. </p>
                              <p> Before the corpse is buried it is carried to the Mosque. Then
                                 after having recited the <hi rend="italic">Fatka</hi> (a prayer
                                 very similar to our Lord's prayer, which is repeated by all
                                 present) the Iman asks the congregation what they have to testify
                                 concerning the life and morals of the deceased. Each then in his
                                 turn relates those good actions with which he was acquainted. The
                                 body is then washed, and wrapped up like a mummy, so that it cannot
                                 be seen. Drugs and spices are placed in the bier with it, and it is
                                 carried to interment. Before it is lowered into the grave, the Iman
                                 commands silence, saying, "Cease your lamentations for a moment,
                                 and let me instruct this Moslem how to act, when he arrives in <rs type="metaplace" subtype="divin" ref="the_other_world">the other
                                    world</rs>." Then in the ear of the corpse, he directs him how
                                 to answer the Evil Spirit who will not fail to question him
                                 respecting his religion, &amp;c. This lesson finished, he repeats
                                 the <hi rend="italic">Fatka</hi> with all the assistants, and the
                                 body is let down into the grave. After they have thrown earth three
                                 times upon the grave, as the Romans used, they retire. The Iman
                                 only remains, he approaches the grave, stoops down, inclines his
                                 ear, and listens to hear if the Dead disputes when the Angel of
                                 Death comes to take him: then he bids him farewell, and in order to
                                 be well paid, never fails to report to the family the best news of
                                 the dead.</p>
                           </note>
                         crowded round her bier,</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="4999">No tongue reported her good deeds,</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5000">For her no mourners wailed and wept,</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5001">No Iman o'er her perfumed corpse,</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5002">For her soul's health intoned the prayer;</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5003">No column
                           <note type="author" anchored="true" xml:id="N_163">
                              <p>
                                 <rs type="place" ref="Turkey">The Turks bury not at all within the
                                    walls of the city</rs>, but the great Turkish Emperors
                                 themselves, with their wives and children about them, and some few
                                 other of their great Bassaes, and those only in chappels by
                                 themselves built for that purpose. All the rest of the Turks are
                                 buried in the fields; some of the better sort in tombs of marble,
                                 but the rest with tomb-stones laid upon them, or with two great
                                 stones, one set up at the head and the other at the feet of every
                                    <rs type="metaplace" subtype="under" ref="Tombs">grave</rs>; the
                                 greatest part of them being of white marble, brought from the Isle
                                 of Marmora. </p>
                              <p> They will not bury any man where another hath been buried,
                                 accounting it impiety to dig up another man's bones: by reason
                                 whereof they cover all the best ground about the city with such
                                 great white stones: which, for the infinite number of them, are
                                 thought sufficient to make another wall about the city.
                                    <bibl>Knolles.</bibl>
                              </p>
                              <p> The Turks bury by the way-side, believing that the passengers will
                                 pray for the souls of the dead. <bibl>Tavernier.</bibl>
                              </p>
                           </note>
                         raised by the way side</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5004">Implored the passing traveller</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5005">To say a requiem for the dead.</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5006">Thalaba laid her in the snow,</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5007">And took his weapons from the hearth,</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5008">And then once more the youth began</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5009">His weary way of solitude.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg565">
                     <l rend="i2" n="5010">
                        <rs type="place" ref="land_of_snow">The breath of the
                           East is in his face</rs>
                     </l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5011">And it drives the sleet and the snow.</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5012">The air is keen, the wind is keen,</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5013">His limbs are aching with the cold,</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5014">His eyes are aching
                           <note type="author" anchored="true" xml:id="N_164">
                              <p> All that day we travelled over <rs type="place" ref="land_of_snow">plains all covered with snow</rs> as the day before, and indeed
                                 it is not only troublesome but very dangerous to travel thro' these
                                 deep snows. The mischief is that the beams of the sun which lie all
                                 day long upon it, molest the eyes and face with such a scorching
                                 beat as very much weakens the sight, whatever remedy a man can
                                 apply, by wearing as the people of the country do, a thin
                                 handkerchief of green or black silk, which no way abates the
                                 annoyance. <bibl>Chardin.</bibl>
                              </p>
                              <p> When they have to travel many days thro' <rs type="place" ref="land_of_snow">a country covered with snow</rs>, Travellers
                                 to preserve their sight, cover the face with a silk kerchief made
                                 on purpose, like a sort of black crape. Others have large furred
                                 bonnets, bordered with goat skin, and the long goat-hair hanging
                                 over the face is as serviceable as the crape.
                                    <bibl>Tavernier.</bibl>
                              </p>
                              <p> An Abyssinian historian says, that the village, called
                                    <placeName>Zinzenam</placeName>, <hi rend="italic">rain upon
                                    rain</hi>, has its name from an extraordinary circumstance that
                                 once happened in these parts, for a shower of rain fell, which was
                                 not properly of the nature of rain, as it did not run upon the
                                 ground, but remained very light, having scarce the weight of
                                 feathers, of a beautiful white colour like flower; it fell in
                                 showers, and occasioned a darkness in the air more than rain, and
                                 liker to mist. It covered the face of the whole country for several
                                 days, retaining its whiteness the whole time, then went away like
                                 dew, without leaving any smell, or unwholsome effect behind it. </p>
                              <p> So the Dutch were formerly expelled from <rs type="place" ref="India">an East Indian Settlement</rs>, because their
                                 Consul, in narrating to the Prince of the Country the wonders of
                                    <placeName>Europe</placeName>, chanced to say that in his own
                                 Country, Water became a solid body once a year, for some time: when
                                 Men or even Horses might pass over it without sinking.—The prince
                                 in a rage said that he had hitherto listened to his tales with
                                 patience, but this was so palpable a Lie, that he would never more
                                 be connected with Europeans, who only could assert such monstrous
                                 falshoods.</p>
                           </note>
                         with the snow,</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5015">His very heart is cold,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5016">His spirit chilled within him. He looks on</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5017">If ought of life be near,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5018">But all is sky and the <placeName ref="land_of_snow">white wilderness</placeName>,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5019">And here and there a solitary pine,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5020">Its branches broken by the weight of snow.</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5021">His pains abate, his senses dull</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5022">With suffering, cease to suffer.</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5023">Languidly, languidly,</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5024">Thalaba drags along,</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5025">A heavy weight is on his lids,</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5026">His limbs move slow with heaviness,</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5027">And he full fain would sleep.</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5028">Not yet, not yet, O Thalaba!</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5029">Thy hour of rest is come;</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5030">Not yet may the Destroyer sleep</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5031">The comfortable sleep,</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5032">His journey is not over yet,</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5033">His course not yet fulfilled;...</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5034">Run thou thy race, O Thalaba!</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5035">The prize is at the goal.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg566">
                     <l rend="i4" n="5036">It was a Cedar-tree</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5037">That woke him from the deadly drowsiness;</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5038">Its broad, round-spreading
                           <note type="author" anchored="true" xml:id="N_165">
                              <p> A strange account of the Cedars of <placeName>Lebanon</placeName>
                                 is given by <bibl>De la Roque. <hi rend="italic">Voyage de Syrie
                                       &amp; du Mont Liban.</hi> 1722</bibl>. </p>
                              <p> "This little forest is composed of twenty Cedars of a prodigious
                                 size, so large indeed that the finest Planes, Sycamores, and other
                                 large trees which we had seen could not be compared with them.
                                 Besides these principal Cedars, there were a great number of lesser
                                 ones, and some very small, mingled with the large trees, or in
                                 little clumps near them. They differed not in their foliage, which
                                 resembles the Juniper, and is green throughout the year: but the
                                 great Cedars spread at their summit and form a perfect round,
                                 whereas the small ones rise in a pyramidal form like the Cypress.
                                 Both diffuse the same pleasant odour; the large ones only yield
                                 fruit, a large cone in shape almost like that of the Pine, but of a
                                 browner colour, and compacter shell. It gives a very pleasant
                                 odour, and contains a sort of thick and transparent balm, which
                                 oozes out thro' small apertures, and falls drop by drop. This fruit
                                 which it is difficult to separate from the stalk, contains a nut
                                 like that of the Cypress; it grows at the end of the boughs, and
                                 turns its point upwards. </p>
                              <p> The nature of this tree is not to elevate its trunk, or the part
                                 between the root and the first branches; for the largest Cedars
                                 which we saw did not in the height of their trunks exceed six or
                                 seven feet. From this low but enormously thick body, prodigious
                                 branches rise, spreading as they rise, and forming by the
                                 disposition of their boughs and leaves which point upward, a sort
                                 of wheel which appears to be the work of art. The bark of the
                                 cedar, except at the trunk, is smooth and shining, of a brown
                                 colour. Its wood white and soft immediately under the bark, but
                                 hard and red within, and very bitter, which renders it
                                 incorruptible and almost immortal. A fragrant gum issues from the
                                 tree. </p>
                              <p> The largest Cedar which we measured was seven feet in
                                 circumference, wanting two inches, and the whole extent of its
                                 branches, which it was easy to measure from their perfect
                                 roundness, formed a circumference of about 120 feet. </p>
                              <p> The Patriarch of the Maronites, fully persuaded of the rarity of
                                 these Trees, and wishing by the preservation of those that remain
                                 to shew his respect for a forest so celebrated in Scripture has
                                 pronounced canonical pains, and even excommunication against any
                                 Christians who shall dare to cut them; scarcely will he permit a
                                 little to be sometimes taken for Crucifixes and little tabernacles
                                 in the chapels of our Missionaries. </p>
                              <p> The Maronites themselves have such a veneration for these Cedars,
                                 that on the day of Transfiguration they celebrate the festival
                                 under them with great solemnity, the Patriarch officiates and says
                                 Mass pontifically, and among other exercises of devotion they
                                 particularly honour the Virgin Mary there, and sing her praises,
                                 because she is compared to the Cedars of
                                    <placeName>Lebanon</placeName>, and Lebanon itself used as a
                                 metaphor for the mother of Christ. </p>
                              <p> The Maronites say that the snows have no sooner begun to fall than
                                 these Cedars, whose boughs in their infinite number are all so
                                 equal in height that they appear to have been shorn, and form, as
                                 we have said, a sort of wheel or parasol,—than these Cedars, I say,
                                 never fail at that time to change their figure. The branches which
                                 before spread themselves rise insensibly, gathering together it may
                                 be said, and turn their points upward towards Heaven, forming
                                 altogether a pyramid. It is <name type="myth">Nature</name>, they
                                 say, who inspires this movement, and makes them assume a new shape,
                                 without which these Trees never could sustain the immense weight of
                                 snow, remaining for so long a time. </p>
                              <p> I have procured more particular information of this fact, and it
                                 has been confirmed by the testimony of many persons, who have often
                                 witnessed it. This is what the Secretary of the Maronite Patriarch
                                 wrote to me in one of his letters, which I think it right to give
                                 in his own words. <hi rend="italic">Cedri Libani quas plantavit
                                    Deus, ut Psalmist: loquitur, sitae sunt in planitie quâdam,
                                    aliquantulum infra altissimum Montis-Libani cacumen, ubi tempore
                                    hyemali maxima nivium quantitas descendit, tribusque &amp;
                                    ultra, mensibus mordaciter dominatur. Cedri in altum ascendunt
                                    extensis tamen ramis in gyrum solo parallelis, confioientibus
                                    suo gyro fere umbellam solarem. Sed superveniente nive, quia
                                    coacervaretur in magnâ quantitate eos desuper, neque possent
                                    pati tantum pondus tanto tempore premens, sine certo fractionis
                                    discrimine, Natura, rerum omnium provida mater, ipsis concessit,
                                    ut adveniente hyeme &amp; descendente nive, statim rami in altum
                                    assurgant, &amp; secum invicem uniti constituant quasi conum, ut
                                    melius sese ab adveniente hoste tueantur. Naturá enim ipsâ verum
                                    est, virtutem quamlebet unitam simul reddi fortiorem.</hi>
                              </p>
                              <p> The Cedars of <placeName>Lebanon</placeName>, which, as the
                                 Psalmist says, God himself planted, are situated in a little plain,
                                 somewhat below the loftiest summit of mount Lebanon, where in the
                                 winter a great quantity of snow falls, and continues for three
                                 months, or longer. The Cedars are high, but their boughs spread out
                                 parallel with the ground into a circle, forming almost a shield
                                 against the sun. But when the snow falls, which would be heaped
                                 upon them in so great a quantity, that they could not endure such a
                                 weight so long a time, without the certain danger of breaking,
                                    <name type="myth">Nature, the provident mother of all</name>,
                                 has endued them with power, that when the winter comes and the snow
                                 descends, their boughs immediately rise, and uniting together form
                                 a cone, that they may be the better defended from the coming Enemy.
                                 For in <name type="myth">Nature</name> itself it is true, that
                                 virtue as it is united, becomes stronger.</p>
                           </note>
                         branches when they felt</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5039">
                        <rs type="place" ref="land_of_snow">The snow, rose
                           upward</rs> in a point to <rs type="metaplace" subtype="celest" ref="Heaven">heaven</rs>,</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5040">And standing in their strength erect,</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5041">Defied the baffled storm.</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5042">He knew the lesson <name type="myth">Nature</name>
                        gave,</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5043">And he shook off his heaviness,</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5044">And hope revived within him.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg567">
                     <l rend="i4" n="5045">Now sunk the evening sun,</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5046">A broad, red, beamless orb,</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5047">Adown the glowing sky;</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5048">Thro' the red light the snow-flakes fell, like fire.</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5049">Louder grows the biting wind,</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5050">
                        <rs type="place" ref="land_of_snow">And it drifts the
                           dust of the snow</rs>.</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5051">The snow is clotted in his hair,</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5052">The breath of Thalaba</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5053">Is iced upon his lips.</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5054">He looks around, the darkness,</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5055">The dizzy floating of the snow,</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5056">Close in his narrow view.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg568">
                     <l rend="i0" n="5057">At length thro' the thick atmosphere a light</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5058">Not distant far appears.</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5059">He doubting other wiles of enmity,</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5060">With mingled joy and quicker step,</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5061">Bends his way thitherward.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg569">
                     <l rend="i0" n="5062">
                        <rs type="metaplace" subtype="garden" ref="Laila_zone">It
                           was a little, lowly dwelling place</rs>,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5063">Amid a garden, whose delightful air</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5064">Felt mild and fragrant, as the evening wind</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5065">Passing in summer o'er the coffee-groves
                           <note type="author" anchored="true" xml:id="N_166">
                              <p> The Coffee plant is about the size of the orange tree, the flower
                                 in colour, size, and smell, resembles the white jessamine, the
                                 berry is first green, then red, in which ripe state it is gathered. </p>
                              <p> Olearius's description of Coffee is amusing. "They drink a certain
                                 black water which they call Cahwa, made of a fruit brought out of
                                    <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, and which is in colour like
                                 ordinary wheat, and in taste like Turkish wheat, and is of the
                                 bigness of a little bean. They fry, or rather burn it in an iron
                                 pan without any liquor, beat it to powder, and boyling it with fair
                                 water, they make this drink thereof, which hath as it were the
                                 taste of a burnt crust, and is not pleasant to the palate. <bibl>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Amb. Travels.</hi>
                                 </bibl>
                              </p>
                           </note>
                        
                     </l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5066">Of <placeName>Yemen</placeName> and its blessed bowers of
                        balm.</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5067">A Fount of Fire that in the centre played,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5068">Rolled all around its wonderous rivulets</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5069">And fed <rs type="metaplace" subtype="garden" ref="Laila_zone">the garden</rs> with the heat of life.</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5070">Every where magic! the Arabian's heart</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5071">Yearned after human intercourse.</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5072">A light!... the door unclosed!...</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5073">All silent ... he goes in.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg570">
                     <l rend="i0" n="5074">
                        <rs type="metaplace" subtype="garden" ref="Laila_zone">There</rs> lay a Damsel sleeping on a couch,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5075">His step awoke her, and she gazed at him</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5076">With pleased and wondering look,</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5077">Fearlessly, like a yearling child</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5078">Too ignorant to fear.</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5079">With words of courtesy</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5080">The young intruder spake.</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5081">At the sound of his voice a joy</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5082">Kindled her bright black eyes;</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5083">She rose and took his hand,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5084">But at the touch the smile forsook her cheek,</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5085">"Oh! it is cold!" she cried,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5086">"I thought I should have felt it warm like mine,</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5087">"But thou art like the rest!"</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg571">
                     <l rend="i4" n="5088">Thalaba stood mute awhile</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5089">And wondering at her words:</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5090">"Cold? Lady!" then he said; "I have travelled long</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5091">"In this cold wilderness,</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5092">"Till life is almost spent!"</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg572">
                     <l rend="i8" n="5093">LAILA.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg573">
                     <l rend="i0" n="5094">Art thou a Man then?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg574">
                     <l rend="i8" n="5095">THALABA.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg575">
                     <l rend="i8" n="5096">I did not think</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5097">Sorrow and toil could so have altered me,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5098">That I seem otherwise.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg576">
                     <l rend="i8" n="5099">LAILA.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg577">
                     <l rend="i8" n="5100"> And thou canst be warm</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5101">Sometimes? life-warm as I am?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg578">
                     <l rend="i8" n="5102">THALABA.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg579">
                     <l rend="i12" n="5103">Surely Lady</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5104">As others are, I am, to heat and cold</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5105">Subject like all, you see a Traveller,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5106">Bound upon hard adventure, who requests</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5107">Only to rest him <rs type="metaplace" subtype="garden" ref="Laila_zone">here</rs> to-night, to-morrow</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5108">He will pursue his way.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg580">
                     <l rend="i8" n="5109">LAILA.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg581">
                     <l rend="i8" n="5110"> Oh ... not to-morrow!</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5111">Not like a dream of joy, depart so soon!</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5112">And whither wouldst thou go? for all around</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5113">
                        <rs type="place" ref="land_of_snow">Is everlasting
                           winter, ice and snow</rs>,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5114">Deserts unpassable of endless frost.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg582">
                     <l rend="i8" n="5115">THALABA.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg583">
                     <l rend="i0" n="5116">He who has led me <rs type="metaplace" subtype="garden" ref="Laila_zone">here</rs> will still sustain me</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5117">Thro' cold and hunger.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg584">
                     <l rend="i4" n="5118">"Hunger?" Laila cried;</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5119">She clapt her lilly hands,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5120">And <rs type="metaplace" subtype="garden" ref="Laila_zone">whether from above or from below</rs>
                     </l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5121">It came, sight could not see,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5122">So suddenly the floor was spread with food.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg585">
                     <l rend="i8" n="5123">LAILA.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg586">
                     <l rend="i0" n="5124">Why dost thou watch with hesitating eyes</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5125">The banquet? 'tis for thee! I bade it come.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg587">
                     <l rend="i8" n="5126">THALABA.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg588">
                     <l rend="i0" n="5127">Whence came it?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg589">
                     <l rend="i8" n="5128">LAILA.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg590">
                     <l rend="i6" n="5129"> Matters it from whence it came</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5130">My father sent it: when I call, he hears.</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5131">Nay ... thou hast fabled with me! and art like</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5132">The forms that wait upon my solitude,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5133">Human to eye alone;... thy hunger would not</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5134">Question so idly else.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg591">
                     <l rend="i8" n="5135">THALABA.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg592">
                     <l rend="i8" n="5136">I will not eat!</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5137">It came by magic! fool to think that aught</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5138">But fraud and danger could await me here!</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5139">Let loose my cloak!...</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg593">
                     <l rend="i8" n="5140">LAILA.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg594">
                     <l rend="i8" n="5141"> Begone then, insolent!</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5142">Why dost thou stand and gaze upon my face?</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5143">Aye! watch the features well that threaten thee</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5144">With fraud and danger! in the wilderness</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5145">They shall avenge me,... in the hour of want</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5146">Rise on thy view, and make thee feel</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5147">How innocent I am:</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5148">And this remembered cowardice and insult</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5149">With a more painful shame will burn thy cheek</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5150">Than now beats mine in anger!</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg595">
                     <l rend="i8" n="5151">THALABA.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg596">
                     <l rend="i12" n="5152">Mark me Lady!</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5153">Many and restless are my enemies;</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5154">My daily paths have been beset with snares</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5155">Till I have learnt suspicion, bitter sufferings</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5156">Teaching the needful vice, if I have wronged you,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5157">And yours should be the face of innocence,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5158">I pray you pardon me! in the name of God,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5159">And of his Prophet, I partake your food.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg597">
                     <l rend="i8" n="5160">LAILA.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg598">
                     <l rend="i0" n="5161">Lo now! thou wert afraid of sorcery,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5162">And yet hast said a charm!</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg599">
                     <l rend="i8" n="5163">THALABA.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg600">
                     <l rend="i10" n="5164">A charm?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg601">
                     <l rend="i8" n="5165">LAILA.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg602">
                     <l rend="i14" n="5166">And wherefore?</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5167">Is it not not delicate food? what mean thy words?</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5168">I have heard many spells and many names</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5169">That rule the Genii and the Elements,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5170">But never these.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg603">
                     <l rend="i8" n="5171">THALABA.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg604">
                     <l rend="i6" n="5172">How! never heard the names</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5173">Of<name type="divin">God</name>and of the Prophet?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg605">
                     <l rend="i8" n="5174">LAILA.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg606">
                     <l rend="i11" n="5175">Never ... nay now</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5176">Again that troubled eye? thou art a strange man</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5177">And wonderous fearful ... but I must not twice</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5178">Be charged with fraud! if thou suspectest still,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5179">Depart and leave me!</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg607">
                     <l rend="i8" n="5180">THALABA.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg608">
                     <l rend="i8" n="5181">And you do not know</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5182">The<name type="divin">God</name>that made you?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg609">
                     <l rend="i8" n="5183">LAILA.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg610">
                     <l rend="i10" n="5184">Made me, man! my Father</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5185">Made me. He made <rs type="metaplace" subtype="garden" ref="Laila_zone">this dwelling, and the grove</rs>,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5186">And yonder fountain-fire, and every morn</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5187">He visits me, and takes the snow, and moulds</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5188">Women and men, like thee; and breathes into them</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5189">Motion, and life, and sense,... but to the touch</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5190">They are chilling cold, and ever when night closes</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5191">They melt away again, and leave me here</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5192">Alone and sad. Oh then how I rejoice</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5193">When it is day and my dear Father comes,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5194">And chears me with kind words and kinder looks!</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5195">My dear, dear, Father! were it not for him,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5196">I am so weary of this loneliness,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5197">That I should wish I also were of snow</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5198">That I might melt away, and cease to be.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg611">
                     <l rend="i8" n="5199">THALABA.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg612">
                     <l rend="i0" n="5200">And have you always had your dwelling <rs type="metaplace" subtype="garden" ref="Laila_zone">here</rs>
                     </l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5201">Amid this solitude of snow?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg613">
                     <l rend="i8" n="5202">LAILA.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg614">
                     <l rend="i11" n="5203">I think so.</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5204">I can remember with unsteady feet</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5205">Tottering from room to room, and finding pleasure</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5206">In flowers and toys and sweetmeats, things that long</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5207">Have lost their power to please; that when I see them</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5208">Raise only now a melancholy wish</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5209">I were the little trifler once again</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5210">That could be pleased so lightly!</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg615">
                     <l rend="i8" n="5211">THALABA.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg616">
                     <l rend="i12" n="5212">Then you know not</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5213">Your Father's art?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg617">
                     <l rend="i8" n="5214">LAILA.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg618">
                     <l rend="i8" n="5215">No. I besought him once</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5216">To give me power like his, that where he went</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5217">I might go with him: but he shook his head,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5218">And said it was a power too dearly bought,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5219">And kist me with the tenderness of tears.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg619">
                     <l rend="i8" n="5220">THALABA.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg620">
                     <l rend="i0" n="5221">And wherefore has he hidden you <rs type="metaplace" subtype="garden" ref="Laila_zone">thus far</rs>
                     </l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5222">From all the ways of humankind?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg621">
                     <l rend="i8" n="5223">LAILA.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg622">
                     <l rend="i12" n="5224">'Twas fear,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5225">Fatherly fear and love. He read
                           <note type="author" anchored="true" xml:id="N_167">
                              <p> It is well known how much the Orientalists are addicted to this
                                 pretended science. There is a curious instance of public folly in
                                 Sir John Chardin's travels. </p>
                              <p> "Sephie-Mirza was born in the year of the <hi rend="italic">Egire</hi> 1057. for the superstition <rs type="place" ref="Persia">of the Persians</rs> will not let us know the month
                                 or the day. Their addiction to Astrology is such that they
                                 carefully conceal the moments of their Princes birth, to prevent
                                 the casting their nativities, where they might meet perhaps with
                                 something which they should be unwilling to know." </p>
                              <p> At the coronation of this Prince two Astrologers were to be
                                 present, with an Astrolabe in their hands, to take the fortunate
                                 hour, as they term it, and observe the lucky moments that a happy
                                 constellation should point out for proceedings of that importance. </p>
                              <p> Sephie-Mirza having by debauchery materially injured his health,
                                 the Chief Physician was greatly alarmed, "in regard his life
                                 depended upon the King's, or if his life were spared yet he was
                                 sure to lose his estate and his liberty, as happens to all those
                                 who attend the Asiatic Sovereigns, when they die under their care.
                                 The Queen Mother too accused him of treason or ignorance, believing
                                 that since he was her Son's Physician he was obliged to cure him.
                                 This made the Physician at his wits end, so that all his receipts
                                 failing him, he bethought himself of one that was peculiarly his
                                 own invention, and which few physicians would ever have found out,
                                 as not being to be met with neither in Galen nor Hippocrates. What
                                 does he then do, but out of an extraordinary fetch of his wit, he
                                 begins to lay the fault upon the stars and the King's Astrologers,
                                 crying out that they were altogether in the wrong, that if the King
                                 lay in a languishing condition and could not recover his health it
                                 was because they had failed to observe the happy hour, or the
                                 Aspect of a fortunate constellation at the time of his coronation."
                                 The stratagem succeeded, the King was recrowned and by the new name
                                 of Solyman! <bibl>Chardin.</bibl>
                              </p>
                           </note>
                        
                        <rs type="metaplace" subtype="celest" ref="stars">the stars</rs>
                     </l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5226">And saw a danger in my destiny,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5227">And therefore placed me here <rs type="place" ref="land_of_snow">amid the snows</rs>,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5228">And laid a spell that never human eye,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5229">If foot of man by chance should reach the depth</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5230">Of this wide waste, shall see one trace of grove,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5231">
                        <rs type="metaplace" subtype="garden" ref="Laila_zone">Garden, or dwelling-place, or yonder fire</rs>,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5232">That thaws and mitigates the frozen sky.</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5233">And more than this, even if the enemy</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5234">Should come, I have a guardian here.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg623">
                     <l rend="i8" n="5235">THALABA.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg624">
                     <l rend="i14" n="5236">A guardian?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg625">
                     <l rend="i8" n="5237">LAILA.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg626">
                     <l rend="i0" n="5238">'Twas well that when my sight unclosed upon thee</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5239">There was no dark suspicion in thy face.</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5240">Else I had called his succour! wilt thou see him?</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5241">But if a Woman can have terrified thee,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5242">How wilt thou bare his unrelaxing brow</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5243">And lifted lightnings?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg627">
                     <l rend="i8" n="5244">THALABA.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg628">
                     <l rend="i8" n="5245">Lead me to him, Lady!</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg629">
                     <l rend="i4" n="5246">She took him by the hand</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5247">And thro' the porch they past.</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5248">Over <rs type="metaplace" subtype="garden" ref="Laila_zone">the garden and the grove</rs>
                     </l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5249">The fountain streams of fire</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5250">Poured a broad light like noon.</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5251">A broad unnatural light</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5252">That made the Rose's blush of beauty pale,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5253">And dimmed the rich Geranium's scarlet blaze.</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5254">The various verdure of the grove</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5255">Now wore one undistinguishable grey,</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5256">Checqured with blacker shade.</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5257">Suddenly Laila stopt,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5258">"I do not think thou art the enemy,"</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5259">She said, "but He will know!</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5260">"If thou hast meditated wrong</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5261">"Stranger, depart in time....</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5262">"I would not lead thee to thy death!"</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg630">
                     <l rend="i4" n="5263">The glance of Laila's eye</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5264">Turned anxiously toward the Arabian youth.</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5265">"So let him pierce my heart," cried Thalaba,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5266">"If it hide thought to harm you!"</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg631">
                     <l rend="i8" n="5267">LAILA.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg632">
                     <l rend="i12" n="5268">'Tis a figure,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5269">Almost I fear to look at!... yet come on.</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5270">'Twill ease me of a heaviness that seems</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5271">To sink my heart; and thou mayest dwell here then.</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5272">In safety;... for thou shalt not go to-morrow,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5273">Nor on the after, nor the after day,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5274">Nor ever! it was only solitude</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5275">That made my misery here,...</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5276">And now that I can see a human face,</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5277">And hear a human voice....</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5278">Oh no! thou wilt not leave me!</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg633">
                     <l rend="i8" n="5279">THALABA.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg634">
                     <l rend="i4" n="5280">Alas I must not rest!</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5281">
                        <rs type="metaplace" subtype="celest" ref="stars">The
                           star that ruled at my nativity</rs>
                     </l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5282">Shone with a strange and blasting influence.</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5283">O gentle Lady! I should draw upon you</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5284">A killing curse.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg635">
                     <l rend="i8" n="5285">LAILA.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg636">
                     <l rend="i6" n="5286">But I will ask my Father</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5287">To save you from all danger, and you know not</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5288">The wonders he can work, and when I ask</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5289">It is not in his power to say me nay.</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5290">Perhaps thou knowest the happiness it is</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5291">To have a tender father?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg637">
                     <l rend="i8" n="5292">THALABA.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg638">
                     <l rend="i10" n="5293">He was one</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5294">Whom like a loathsome leper I have tainted</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5295">With my contagious destiny. At evening</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5296">He kist me as he wont, and laid his hands</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5297">Upon my head, and blest me ere I slept.</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5298">His dying groan awoke me, for the Murderer</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5299">Had stolen upon our sleep! for me was meant</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5300">The midnight blow of death; my father died,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5301">The brother play-mates of my infancy,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5302">The baby at the breast, they perished all,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5303">All in that dreadful hour: but I was saved</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5304">To remember and revenge.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg639">
                     <l rend="i4" n="5305">She answered not, for now</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5306">Emerging from the o'er-arched avenue</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5307">The finger of her upraised hand</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5308">Marked where the Guardian of <rs type="metaplace" subtype="garden" ref="Laila_zone">the garden</rs> stood.</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5309">It was a brazen
                           <note type="author" anchored="true" xml:id="N_168">
                              <p> We have now to refute their errour who are persuaded that Brazen
                                 Heads made under certain constellations may give answers, and be as
                                 it were guides and counsellors, upon all occasions, to those that
                                 had them in their possession. Among these is one Yepes who affirms
                                 that Henry de Villeine made such a one at
                                    <placeName>Madrid</placeName>, broken to pieces afterwards by
                                 order of John 2. King of Castile. The same thing is affirmed by
                                 Bartholomew Sibillus, and the Author of <title>the <hi rend="italic">Image of the World</hi>
                              </title>, of Virgil; by
                                 William of Malmsbury of Sylvester; by John Gower of Robert of
                                    <placeName>Lincoln</placeName>; by the common people of
                                    <placeName>England</placeName> of Roger Bacon; and by Tostatus
                                 Bishop of <placeName>Avilla</placeName>, George of
                                    <placeName>Venice</placeName>, Delrio, Sibillus, Raguseus,
                                 Delancre and others, too many to mention, of Albertus Magnus; who
                                 as the most expert, had made an entire man of the same metal, and
                                 had spent thirty years without any interruption in forming him <rs type="metaplace" subtype="celest" ref="stars">under several
                                    aspects and constellations</rs>. For example, he formed the
                                 eyes, according to the said Tostatus in his commentaries upon
                                 Exodus, when the Sun was in a sign of the Zodiac correspondent to
                                 that part, casting them out of divers metals mixt together and
                                 mark'd with the characters of the same signs and planets, and their
                                 several and necessary aspects. The same method he observed in the
                                 head, neck, shoulders, thighs, and legs, all which were fashioned
                                 at several times, and being put and fastened together in the form
                                 of a man, had the faculty to reveal to the said Albertus the
                                 solutions of all his principal difficulties. To which they add
                                 (that nothing be lost of the story of the statue) that it was
                                 battered to pieces by St. Thomas, meerely because he could not
                                 endure its excesse of prating. </p>
                              <p> But to give a more rational account of this Androides of Albertus,
                                 as also of all these miraculous heads, I conceive the original of
                                 this fable may well be deduced from the Teraph of the Hebrews, by
                                 which as Mr. Selden affirms, many are of opinion, that we must
                                 understand what is said in Genesis concerning Laban's Gods, and in
                                 the first book of Kings concerning the image which Michol put into
                                 the bed in David's place. For R. Eleazar holds that it was made of
                                 the head of a male child, the first born and that dead-born, under
                                 whose tongue they applyed a lamen of Gold, whereon were engraved
                                 the characters and inscriptions of certain planets, which the Jews
                                 superstitiously wandered up and down with, instead of the Urim and
                                 Thummim, or the Ephod of the High Priest. And that this original is
                                 true and well deduced, there is a manifest indicium, in that Henry
                                 D'Assia, and Bartholomæus Sibillus affirm, that the Androides of
                                 Albertus, and the Head made by Virgil, were composed of flesh and
                                 bone, yet not by nature, but by art. But this being judged
                                 impossible by modern Authors, and the vertue of Images, Annulets,
                                 and planetary Sigills being in great reputation, men have thought
                                 ever since (taking their opinion from Trismegistus affirming in his
                                 Asclepion, that of the Gods, some were made by the Sovereign God,
                                 and others by men, who, by some art, had the power to unite the
                                 invisible Spirits to things visible and corporeal, as is explained
                                 at large by St. Augustine) that such figures were made of copper or
                                 some other metal, whereon men had wrought under some favourable
                                 Aspects of Heaven and the planets. </p>
                              <p> My design is not absolutely to deny that he might compose some
                                 head or statue of man, like that of Memnon, from which proceeded a
                                 small sound and pleasant noise, when the rising Sun came by his
                                 heat to rarify and force out, by certain small conduits, the air
                                 which in the cold of the night was condensed within it. Or haply
                                 they might be like those statues of Boetius, whereof Cassiodorus
                                 speaking said, <hi rend="italic">Metalla mugiunt</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Diomedis in ære grues buccinant, ænus anguis
                                    insibilat, aves simulatæ fritinniunt, et quæ propriam vocem
                                    nesciunt, ab ære dulcedinem probantur emittere cantilenæ</hi>;
                                 for such I doubt not but may be made by the help of that part of
                                 Natural Magic which depends on the Mathematics. <bibl>History of
                                    Magic.</bibl>
                              </p>
                              <p> The title page to this book is wanting;, but the Epistle
                                 Dedicatory is signed J. Davies. By the stile, spelling, and <hi rend="italic">extensive reading of the author</hi>, it appears
                                 to be a work of the last century.</p>
                           </note>
                         Image, every limb</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5310">And swelling vein and muscle, true to life:</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5311">The left knee bending on,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5312">The other straight, firm planted, and his hand</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5313">Lifted on high to hurl</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5314">The Lightning that it grasped.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg640">
                     <l rend="i4" n="5315">When Thalaba approached,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5316">The charmed Image knew Hodeirah's son,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5317">And hurled the lightning at the dreaded foe.</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5318">The Ring! the saviour Ring!</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5319">Full in his face the lightning-bolt was driven,</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5320">The scattered fire recoiled.</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5321">Like the flowing of a summer gale he felt</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5322">Its ineffectual force,</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5323">His countenance was not changed,</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5324">Nor a hair of his head was singed.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg641">
                     <l rend="i4" n="5325">He started and his glance</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5326">Turned angrily upon the Maid,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5327">The sight disarmed suspicion ... breathless, pale,</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5328">Against a tree she stood.</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5329">Her wan lips quivering, and her eye</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5330">Upraised, in silent supplicating fear.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg642">
                     <l rend="i2" n="5331">She started with a scream of joy</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5332">Seeing her Father there,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5333">And ran and threw her arms around his neck,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5334">"Save me!" she cried, "the Enemy is come!</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5335">"Save me! save me! Okba!"</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg643">
                     <l rend="i4" n="5336">"Okba!" repeats the youth,</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5337">For never since that hour</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5338">When in the Tent the Spirit told his name,</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5339">Had Thalaba let slip</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5340">The memory of his Father's murderer;</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5341">"Okba!"... and in his hand</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5342">He graspt an arrow-shaft.</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5343">And he rushed on to strike him.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg644">
                     <l rend="i0" n="5344">"Son of Hodeirah!" the Old Man replied,</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5345">"My hour is not yet come."</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5346">And putting forth his hand</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5347">Gently he repelled the Youth.</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5348">"My hour is not yet come!</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5349">"But thou mayest shed this innocent Maiden's blood,</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5350">"That vengeance<name type="divin">God</name>allows
                        thee."</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg645">
                     <l rend="i4" n="5351">Around her Father's neck</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5352">Still Laila's hands were clasped.</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5353">Her face was turned to Thalaba,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5354">A broad light floated o'er its marble paleness,</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5355">As the wind waved <rs type="metaplace" subtype="garden" ref="Laila_zone">the fountain fire</rs>.</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5356">Her large, dilated eye in horror raised</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5357">Watched his every movement.</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5358">"Not upon her," said he,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5359">"Not upon her Hodeirah's blood cries out</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5360">"For vengeance!" and again his lifted arm</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5361">Threatened the Sorcerer,</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5362">Again withheld it felt</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5363">The barrier that no human strength could burst.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg646">
                     <l rend="i0" n="5364">"Thou dost not aim the blow more eagerly,"</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5365">Okba replied, "than I would rush to meet it!</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5366">"But that were poor revenge.</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5367">"O Thalaba, thy<name type="divin">God</name>
                     </l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5368">"Wreaks on the innocent head</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5369">"His vengeance;... I must suffer in my child!</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5370">"Why dost thou pause to strike thy victim? <name type="divin">Allah</name>
                     </l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5371">"Permits, commands the deed."</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg647">
                     <l rend="i4" n="5372">"Liar!" quoth Thalaba.</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5373">And Laila's wondering eye</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5374">Looked up, all anguish to her Father's face,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5375">"By <name type="divin">Allah</name> and the Prophet," he
                        replied,</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5376">"I speak the words of truth.</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5377">"Misery, misery,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5378">"That I must beg mine enemy to speed</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5379">"The inevitable vengeance now so near!</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5380">"I read it in her horoscope,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5381">"<rs type="metaplace" subtype="celest" ref="stars">Her
                           birth-star</rs> warned me of Hodeirah's race.</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5382">"I laid a spell, and called a Spirit up.</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5383">"He answered one must die</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5384">"Laila or Thalaba....</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5385">"Accursed Spirit! even in truth</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5386">"Giving a lying hope!</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5387">"Last, I ascended <rs type="metaplace" subtype="divin" ref="7th_Heaven">the seventh Heaven</rs>
                     </l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5388">"And on the everlasting
                           <note type="author" anchored="true" xml:id="N_169">
                              <p> This Table is suspended in <rs type="metaplace" subtype="divin" ref="7th_Heaven">the Seventh Heaven</rs>, and guarded from the
                                 Demons, lest they should change or corrupt any thing thereon. Its
                                 length is so great as is the space between <rs type="metaplace" subtype="divin">Heaven</rs> and <placeName ref="Earth_planet">Earth</placeName>, its breadth equal to the distance from the
                                 East to the West, and it is made of one pearl. The divine Pen was
                                 created by the finger of God: that also is of pearls, and of such
                                 length and breadth that a swift horse could scarcely gallop round
                                 it in five hundred years. It is so endowed, that self-moved it
                                 writes all things, past, present, and to come. Light, is its ink,
                                 and the language which it uses, only the Angel Seraphael
                                 understands. <bibl>Maracci.</bibl>
                              </p>
                           </note>
                         Table there</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5389">"In characters of light,</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5390">"I read her written doom.</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5391">"The years that it has gnawn me! and the load</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5392">"Of sin that it has laid upon my soul!</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5393">"Curse on this hand that in the only hour</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5394">"The favouring stars allowed</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5395">"Reeked with other blood than thine.</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5396">"Still dost thou stand and gaze incredulous?</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5397">"Young man, be merciful, and keep her not</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5398">"Longer in agony!"</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg648">
                     <l rend="i2" n="5399">Thalaba's unbelieving frown</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5400">Scowled on the Sorcerer,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5401">When in the air the rush of wings was heard</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5402">And Azrael stood among them.</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5403">In equal terror at the sight</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5404">The Enchanter, the Destroyer stood,</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5405">And Laila, the victim maid.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg649">
                     <l rend="i0" n="5406">"Son of Hodeirah!" said the Angel of Death,</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5407">"The accursed fables not.</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5408">"When from the Eternal Hand I took</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5409">"The yearly
                           <note type="author" anchored="true" xml:id="N_170">
                              <p> They celebrate the night Léïleth-ul-beraeth on the 15th of the
                                 month of Schabann, with great apprehension and terror, because they
                                 consider it as the tremendous night on which the angels
                                 Kiramenn-keatibinn, placed on each side of mankind to write down
                                 their good and bad actions, deliver up their books and receive
                                 fresh ones for the continuance of the same employment. It is
                                 believed also, that on that night the archangel Azrail, the angel
                                 of death, gives up also his records and receives another book in
                                 which are written the names of all those destined to die in the
                                 following year. <bibl>D'Ohsson.</bibl>
                              </p>
                           </note>
                         scroll of fate,</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5410">"Her name was written there.</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5411">"This is the hour, and from thy hands</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5412">"Commissioned to receive the Maid I come."</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg650">
                     <l rend="i0" n="5413">"Hear me O Angel!" Thalaba replied,</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5414">"To avenge my Father's death,</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5415">"To work the will of <rs type="metaplace" subtype="divin">Heaven</rs>,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5416">"To root from <placeName ref="Earth_planet">earth</placeName> the accursed sorcerer race,</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5417">"I have dared danger undismayed,</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5418">"I have lost all my soul held dear,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5419">"I am cut off from all the ties of life,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5420">"Unmurmuring; for whate'er awaits me still,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5421">"Pursuing to the end the enterprize,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5422">"Peril or pain, I bear a ready heart.</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5423">"But strike this Maid! this innocent!</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5424">"Angel, I dare not do it."</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg651">
                     <l rend="i0" n="5425">"Remember," answered Azrael, "all thou sayest</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5426">"Is written down for judgement! every word</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5427">"In the balance of
                           <note type="author" anchored="true" xml:id="N_171">
                              <p> The Balance of the Dead is an article in almost every creed.
                                 Mohammed borrowed it from the Persians. I know not from whence the
                                 Monks introduced it; probably they were ignorant enough to have
                                 invented the obvious fiction. </p>
                              <p> In the Vision of Thurcillus the ceremony is accurately described.
                                    <q>"At the end of the north wall, within the church, sate St.
                                    Paul, and opposite him, without, was <name type="divin">the
                                       Devil</name>and his Angels. At the feet of <name type="divin">the Devil</name>a burning pit flamed up, which was the mouth
                                    of the Pit of Hell. A Balance equally poised, was fixed upon the
                                    wall between <name type="divin">the Devil</name>and the Apostle,
                                    one scale hanging before each. The Apostle had two weights, a
                                    greater and a less, all shining and like gold, and <name type="divin">the Devil</name>also had two smoky and black
                                    ones. Therefore the Souls that were all black came one after
                                    another, with great fear and trembling, to behold the weighing
                                    of their good and evil works: for these weights weighed the
                                    works of all the souls, according to the good or evil which they
                                    had done. When the scale inclined to the Apostle, he took the
                                    Soul, and introduced it thro' the Eastern gate, into the fire of
                                    Purgatory, that there it might expiate its crimes. But when the
                                    scale inclined and sunk towards the Devil, then he and his
                                    Angels snatched the soul miserably howling and cursing the
                                    father and mother that begot it to eternal torments, and cast it
                                    with laughter and grinning into the deep and fiery pit which was
                                    at the feet of <name type="divin">the Devil</name>. Of this
                                    Balance of good and evil much may be found in the writings of
                                    the holy Fathers." <bibl>
                                       <author>Matthew Paris</author>
                                    </bibl>.</q>
                              </p>
                              <q>
                                 <p> "Concerning the salvation of Charlemagne, Archbishop Turpin, a
                                    man of holy life, wrote thus. "I, Turpin, Archbishop of Rheims,
                                    being in my chamber, in the city of Vienna, saying my prayers,
                                    saw a legion of Devils in the air, who were making a great
                                    noise. I adjured one of them to tell me from whence they came,
                                    and wherefore they made so great an uproar. And he replied that
                                    they came from <placeName>Aix la Chapelle</placeName>, where a
                                    great Lord had died, and that they were returning in anger
                                    because they had not been able to carry away his soul. I asked
                                    him who the great Lord was, and why they had not been able to
                                    carry away his soul. He replied that it was Charlemagne, and
                                    that Saint Jago had been greatly against them. And I asked him
                                    how St. Jago had been against them; and he replied, we were
                                    weighing the good and the evil which he had done <placeName ref="the_world">in this world</placeName>, and Saint Jago
                                    brought so much timber and so many stones from the churches
                                    which he had founded in his name, that they greatly
                                    over-balanced all his evil works; and so we had no power over
                                    his soul. And having said this <name type="divin">the
                                       Devil</name>disappeared." </p>
                              </q>
                              <p> We must understand from this vision of Archbishop Turpin, that
                                 they who build or repair churches <placeName ref="the_world">in
                                    this world</placeName>, erect resting places and inns for their
                                 salvation. </p>
                              <p>
                                 <bibl>
                                    <title>
                                       <hi rend="italic">Historia do Imperador Carlos Magno, &amp;
                                          dos Doze Pares de França.</hi>
                                    </title>
                                 </bibl>
                              </p>
                              <p> Two other corollaries follow from the vision. The Devil's way home
                                 from <placeName>Aix la Chapelle</placeName> lay thro'
                                    <placeName>Vienna</placeName>;—and as churches go by weight, an
                                 architect of Sir John Vanbrugh's school should always be employed. </p>
                              <p> This Balance of the Dead was an easy and apt metaphor, but
                                 clumsily imagined as an actual mode of trial. </p>
                              <q>
                                 <lg>
                                    <l rend="i0">"For take thy Ballaunce, if thou be so wise,</l>
                                    <l rend="i1">"And weigh the winde that under heaven doth
                                       blow;</l>
                                    <l rend="i0">"Or weigh the light that in the East doth rise:</l>
                                    <l rend="i1">"Or weigh the thought that from man's mind doth
                                       flow</l>
                                    <l rend="i1">"But if the weight of these thou canst not
                                       show,</l>
                                    <l rend="i0">"Weigh but one word which from thy lips doth
                                       fall."</l>
                                 </lg>
                                 <bibl>
                                    <author>Spenser</author>. </bibl>
                              </q>
                           </note>
                         thy trial must be weighed!"</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg653">
                     <l rend="i4" n="5434">"So be it!" said the Youth.</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5435">"He who can read the secrets of the heart</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5436">"Will judge with righteousness!</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5437">"This is no doubtful path,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5438">"The voice of<name type="divin">God</name>within me
                        cannot lie....</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5439">"I will not harm the innocent."</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg654">
                     <l rend="i4" n="5440">He said, and from above,</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5441">As tho' it were the Voice of Night,</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5442">The startling answer came.</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5443">"Son of Hodeirah, think again!</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5444">"One must depart from <rs type="metaplace" subtype="garden" ref="Laila_zone">hence</rs>,</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5445">"Laila, or Thalaba;</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5446">"She dies for thee, or thou for her,</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5447">"It must be life for life!</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5448">"Son of Hodeirah, weigh it well,</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5449">"While yet the choice is thine!"</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg655">
                     <l rend="i4" n="5450">He hesitated not,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5451">But looking upward spread his hands to <rs type="metaplace" subtype="divin">Heaven</rs>,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5452">"Oneiza, in thy bower of <rs type="metaplace" subtype="divin">Paradise</rs>
                     </l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5453">"Receive me, still unstained!"</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg656">
                     <l rend="i0" n="5454">"What!" exclaimed Okba, "darest thou disobey,</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5455">"Abandoning all claim</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5456">"To <name type="divin">Allah</name>'s longer aid?"</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg657">
                     <l rend="i0" n="5457">The eager exultation of his speech</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5458">
                        <rs type="place" ref="the_world">Earthward</rs> recalled
                        the thoughts of Thalaba.</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5459">"And dost thou triumph, Murderer? dost thou deem</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5460">"Because I perish, that the unsleeping lids</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5461">"Of Justice shall be closed upon thy crime?</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5462">"Poor, miserable man! that thou canst live</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5463">"With such beast-blindness in the present joy</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5464">"When o'er thy head the sword of<name type="divin">God</name>
                     </l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5465">"Hangs for the certain stroke!"</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg658">
                     <l rend="i0" n="5466">"Servant of <name type="divin">Allah</name>, thou hast
                        disobeyed,</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5467">"<name type="divin">God</name> hath abandoned thee,</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5468">"This hour is mine!" cried Okba,</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5469">And shook his Daughter off,</l>
                     <l rend="i2" n="5470">And drew the dagger from his vest.</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5471">And aimed the deadly blow.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="B10_lg659">
                     <l rend="i0" n="5472">All was accomplished. Laila rushed between</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5473">To save the saviour Youth.</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5474">She met the blow and sunk into his arms,</l>
                     <l rend="i0" n="5475">And Azrael from the hands
                           <note type="author" anchored="true" xml:id="N_172">
                              <p> This double meaning is in the spirit of oracular prediction. The
                                 classical reader will remember the equivocations of Apollo, the
                                 fable of the young man and the Lion in the tapestry will be more
                                 generally recollected: we have many buildings in England to which
                                 this story has been applied,—<placeName>Cook's Folly near
                                       <placeName>Bristol</placeName>
                              </placeName> derives its name
                                 from a similar tradition. </p>
                              <p> The History of the Buccaneers affords a remarkable instance of
                                 prophecy occasioning its own accomplishment. </p>
                              <p> "Before my first going over into the <hi rend="italic">
                                 <placeName>South-Seas</placeName>
                              </hi> with Captain <hi rend="italic">Sharp</hi> (and indeed before any Privateers, at
                                 least since <hi rend="italic">Drake</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Oxengham</hi>) had gone that way which we afterwards went,
                                 except <hi rend="italic">La Sound</hi>, a <hi rend="italic">French</hi> Captain, who by Capt. <hi rend="italic">Wright's</hi> instructions had ventured as far as <hi rend="italic">
                                 <placeName>Cheapo</placeName>
                              </hi> town with a
                                 body of men, but was driven back again, I being then on board Capt.
                                    <hi rend="italic">Coxon</hi>, in company with three or four more
                                 Privateers, about four leagues to the East of <hi rend="italic">
                                 <placeName>Portobel</placeName>
                              </hi>, we took the packets
                                 bound thither from <hi rend="italic">
                                 <placeName>Carthagena</placeName>
                              </hi>. We opened a great
                                 quantity of the Merchant's letters, and found the contents of many
                                 of them to be very surprizing, the Merchants of several parts of
                                    <hi rend="italic">
                                 <placeName ref="Spain">Old-Spain</placeName>
                              </hi> thereby informing their
                                 correspondents of <hi rend="italic">
                                 <placeName>Panama</placeName>
                              </hi>, and elsewhere, of a certain
                                 prophecy that went about <hi rend="italic">
                                 <placeName>Spain</placeName>
                              </hi> that year, the tenor of
                                 which was, <hi rend="italic">that there would be</hi> English <hi rend="italic">privateers that year in the</hi>
                                 <placeName ref="West_Indies">West-Indies</placeName>, <hi rend="italic">who would make such great discoveries, as to open
                                    a door into the</hi>
                                 <placeName>South-Seas</placeName>; which they supposed was fastest
                                 shut: and the letters were accordingly full of cautions to their
                                 friends to be very watchful and careful of their coasts. </p>
                              <p> This door they spake of we all concluded must be the passage over
                                 land through <rs type="place" ref="West_Indies">the country of the
                                       <hi rend="italic">Indians</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Darien</hi>
                              </rs>, who were a little before this become our
                                 friends, and had lately fallen out with the <hi rend="italic">Spaniards</hi>, breaking off the intercourse which for some
                                 time they had with them: And upon calling also to mind the frequent
                                 invitations we had from those <hi rend="italic">Indians</hi> a
                                 little before this time, to pass through their Country, and fall
                                 upon the <hi rend="italic">Spaniards</hi> in the <hi rend="italic">South-Seas</hi>, we from henceforward began to entertain such
                                 thoughts in earnest, and soon came to a resolution to make those
                                 attempts which we afterwards did with Capt. <hi rend="italic">Sharp, Coxon, &amp;c.</hi> So that the taking these letters
                                 gave the first life to those bold undertakings: And we took the
                                 advantage of the fears the <hi rend="italic">Spaniards</hi> were in
                                 from that prophecy, or probable conjecture, or whatever it were;
                                 for we sealed up most of the letters again, and sent them ashore to
                                    <hi rend="italic">
                                 <placeName>Portobel</placeName>
                              </hi>.
                                    <bibl>Dampier.</bibl>
                              </p>
                           </note>
                         of Thalaba</l>
                     <l rend="i4" n="5476">
                        <rs type="metaplace" subtype="divin" ref="the_other_world">Received her parting soul</rs>.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
